Guide to the Robin Morgan Papers, 1940s-2019 and undated, bulk 1970-2019 RL.00913
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robin Morgan papers
1940s-2019 and undated, bulk 1970-2019
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Morgan, Robin, 1941-
RL.00913
84.0 Linear Feet
The collection documents the personal, political, and professional aspects of the life of an important feminist writer of the twentieth century. The largest group of materials consists of documentation on all of Morgan's significant written works: DEMON LOVER; DEPTH PERCEPTION; DRY YOUR SMILE; GOING TOO FAR; A HOT JANUARY; LADY OF THE BEASTS; SATURDAY'S CHILD; her well-known feminist anthologies, SISTERHOOD IS POWERFUL, SISTERHOOD IS GLOBAL and SISTERHOOD IS FOREVER; and other materials on her poems, articles, and other writings. In addition, Morgan's papers hold many items of correspondence with a wide range of individuals, including prominent activists and feminists as well as family members and close friends. There is also a significant amount of correspondence and other material that documents Morgan's role as founder of the Sisterhood is Global Institute, and records related to her role as editor and writer for MS. magazine.
Online Items
Selected items from this collection have been digitized and are available in: Women's Liberation Movement Print Culture - Duke Digital Collections.
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Women's Media Center materials closed by donor request.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Robin Morgan Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as purchases from 2001-2003, and as a gift in 2009, 2010, 2015-2016, and 2019.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1941, Jan. 29 Born in Lake Worth, Fla.
1956 Graduated with Honors from the Wetter School
1956-1959 Student with private tutors at Columbia University, ages 15-18
1961-1969 Free-lance book editor
1962 Married Kenneth Pitchford
1968 Organized first feminist demonstration against Miss America Pageant
1969 Birth of son, Blake
1969-1970 Editor for Grove Press
1970 Author, compiler, and editor of Sisterhood is Powerful: An Anthology of Writings from the Women's Liberation Movement
1970 Founder and president of The Sisterhood is Powerful Foundation
1972 Monster: Poems published
1973 Visiting chair and guest professor of Women's Studies at New College, Sarasota, Fla.
1974-1987 Editor and columnist of Ms. magazine
1978 Going Too Far: The Personal Chronicle of a Feminist published
1979-1980 Received National Endowment for the Arts grant
1982 Depth Perception: New Poems and a Masque published
1982-1984 Received Ford Foundation grant
1984 Founder of Sisterhood is Global Institute
1984 Author, compiler, and editor of Sisterhood is Global: The International Women's Movement Anthology
1987 Distinguished visiting scholar and lecturer at Rutgers University, N. J.
1989 The Demon Lover: On the Sexuality of Terrorism published
1989-1993 Editor in chief of Ms. magazine
1990 Divorced from Kenneth Pitchford
1992 Received Honorary Doctorate from the University of Connecticut
1993 Consulting editor of Ms. magazine
1996-1997 Visiting professor at the University of Denver Graduate School of International Affairs
2000 Saturday's Child: A Memoir published
2003 Author, compiler, and editor of Sisterhood is Forever: The Women's Anthology for a New Millennium
2003 Columnist for Ms. magazine
Robin Morgan is a feminist activist, award-winning poet, novelist, journalist, and essayist. She was a child model, had her own radio show at the age of four, and was a child star on television. Since the late 1960s, when she organized the first demonstration against the Miss America Pageant, Morgan has been active in the feminist movement. In 1984, she founded the Sisterhood is Global Institute, an international, non-governmental, and non-profit organization concerned with women's rights which is currently based in Montreal, Canada.
As a recipient of numerous writing grants, Morgan has published eighteen books, including six poetry collections, two books of fiction, the now-classic anthology Sisterhood is Powerful (named by the American Library Association one of the "The 100 Most Influential Books of the 20th Century"), and an anthology of international feminism, Sisterhood is Global. She has also consistently contributed to Ms. magazine. She currently lives in New York.
Collection Overview
The collection documents the personal, political, and professional aspects of the life of an important feminist writer of the twentieth century. It is organized into the following series: Correspondence, Writings, Speeches and Interviews, Subject Files, Personal Files, Teaching Materials, Audio-Visual Materials, Photographic and Visual Materials, and Oversize Material. The largest group of materials consists of documentation on all of Morgan's significant written works: Demon Lover; Depth Perception; Dry Your Smile; Going Too Far; A Hot January; Lady of the Beasts; Saturday's Child; her well-known feminist anthologies, Sisterhood is Powerful and Sisterhood is Global; and other materials on her poems, articles, and other writings. In addition, Morgan's papers hold many items of correspondence with a wide range of individuals, including prominent activists and feminists as well as family members and close friends. There is also a significant amount of correspondence and other material that documents Morgan's role as founder of the Sisterhood is Global Institute, and records related to her role as editor and writer for Ms. magazine.
Seen in a broader context, the collection provides ample documentation for the study of modern feminism. Morgan's subject files (the second largest in the series) are rich in materials related to the feminist movement in the United States and around the world; and materials concerning sexual health, witchcraft, lesbian feminism, and the social, economic, and political position of women in the world (especially in the Middle East, Russia, and South Africa). There are materials on individual figures such as Bella Abzug, Jane Alpert (imprisoned revolutionary), Patty Hearst, Gloria Steinem, and Marilyn Waring. Other series hold additional materials related to Morgan's career as a writer; several of her speeches and interviews; materials from Morgan's courses she gave on feminism; and photographs and audio-visual materials.
The Correspondence Series spans much of Morgan's adult life. It is divided into two subseries: Correspondence by Name and Correspondence by Decade. The Correspondence by Name Subseries chiefly consists of Morgan's correspondence with family members, friends, fellow feminist activists and contemporary authors and critics. The bulk of the items in the Correspondence by Decade Subseries dates from the 1990s and relates to the production of Ms. magazine. The Correspondence Series is restricted: patrons must sign an Acknowledgment of Legal Rights and Responsibilities form before using the materials.
The Writings Series documents Morgan's career as a poet, novelist, essayist and journalist. Of Morgan's eighteen books, ten are represented in individual subseries. Particularly noteworthy is the material related to Sisterhood is Global, which provides an inside view into the production of the anthology. The series also contains some of Morgan's earliest unpublished writings as well as files containing her comments on other writers' work, and single issues of periodicals in which she published her poetry. The Writings Series is also restricted: patrons must sign an Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form before using the materials.
The Speeches and Interviews Series primarily contains peripheral documentation such as contracts, correspondence, and schedules. However, there are drafts of a number of her speeches and interviews.
Materials which Morgan collected over the years concerning American and international feminism are located in the Subject Files Series. The materials cover a number of topics, including women's economic, political, and social status, and feminist action - especially in South Africa, the Soviet Union, and the Middle East; rape, abortion, terrorism, female genital mutilation, and pornography; and the first feminist demonstration against the Miss America Pageant. Significant figures represented in the subject files include Marilyn Waring, Patricia Hearst, and Gloria Steinem. Two subseries contain administrative information about Ms. magazine and the Sisterhood is Global Institute. The Subjects Series is restricted: patrons must sign an Acknowledgment of Legal Rights and Responsibilities form before using the materials.
The smaller Personal Files Series offers materials related to Robin Morgan's education, early critical writing, and her many trips overseas. The series also includes material that Morgan requested under the Freedom of Information Act from the FBI and CIA about her own activities.
The documents in the Teaching Materials Series are primarily related to Morgan's academic positions at New College (Sarasota, Fla.) and the University of Denver, and the courses she taught on feminism and writing. The files include both administrative documentation as well as actual course material, but there are also clippings related to feminist protests on campus.
The Audio-Visual Materials Series contains numerous interviews on cassette tapes that Morgan conducted in the Middle East, a recording of her reading of selected poems from A Hot January, and a videotape about the production of Saturday's Child. Permission is not granted to publish interviews conducted in the Middle East; the researcher is responsible for obtaining permission to publish. Original copies of audiovisual materials are not open to use; however, use copies are available to researchers.
The Photographic and Visual Materials Series provides a small visual supplement to the other documents in the collection and includes portrait photographs of Morgan taken by the press and by her close friends, as well as snapshots of social gatherings. This series also includes two painted portraits of Morgan. The series is restricted: patrons must sign an Acknowledgment of Legal Rights and Responsibilities form before using the materials.
Later additions (Accessions 2009-0069, 2010-0176, 2015-0060) have not been fully processed, but boxlists are available in the Detailed Description portion of this finding aid. Some portions are restricted or closed.
For collections related to the Robin Morgan Papers, see the Phyllis Chesler, Merle Hoffman, and Kate Millett Papers, all located in the Duke University David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library. In addition to Robin Morgan's own papers, the Library also holds the records of the Sisterhood is Global Institute, founded by Morgan in 1984.
Black-and-white photographs; Feminism -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Feminists -- United States; Audiocassettes; Periodical editors -- United States; Feminism -- United States; Periodicals -- Publishing -- United States; Videocassettes; Witchcraft; Women's rights -- Middle East; Feminism -- Middle East; Feminism -- South Africa; Women's rights; Lesbian feminism; Feminists -- United States -- Correspondence; Feminists -- Soviet Union; Color slides; Compact discs; Color negatives; Women's rights -- South Africa; Color photographs; Waring, Marilyn; Morgan, Robin, 1941-; Ms; Steinem, Gloria; Sisterhood is Global Institute; Alpert, Jane; Hearst, Patricia,; Abzug, Bella S., 1920-1998
- Correspondence Series, 1950s-1999 and undated
  Conditions Governing Access note
  [RESTRICTED: Patrons must sign an Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form before using the materials.]
  Scope and Contents note
  The series is divided into two subseries: Correspondence by Name and Correspondence by Decade, both of which contain letters to and from Robin Morgan. The Correspondence by Name Subseries is organized alphabetically by last name or place. Prominent correspondents include feminists such as Simone de Beauvoir, Sallie Bingham, Kate Millett, Adrienne Rich, and Gloria Steinem. There are also letters of a personal nature with Morgan's mother, aunts, and close friends, such as Vladimir Urban. Particularly voluminous is the correspondence from Isel Rivero (further documented in the Photographic and Visual Materials Series), with whom Robin Morgan maintained a close relationship during the 1980s, and from Jane Alpert. The latter provides interesting insights into a woman's life in the underground and in prison during the mid-1970s.
  While there are several letters in the Correspondence by Decade Subseries that date from the 1950s and 1960s (including a letter from Nehru), the bulk of the correspondence comes from the 1990s. Material from this decade includes letters of both a personal and professional nature; one group of folders contains correspondence pertaining solely to the period during which Morgan was Ms. magazine's editor in chief. In this subseries, the correspondence is arranged in original order, by decade only.
  - Correspondence by Name Subseries, 1958-1999 and undated
    - Alpert, Jane (Box C1)
      - Photographs, undated (Box C1)
      - Underground originals, 1971-1973 (Box C1)
      - More underground originals, 1973-1974 (Box C1)
      - Underground, 1971-1974 and undated (Box C1)
      - Kenneth-Jane correspondence, 1972-1974 (Box C1)
      - Press, 1973-1974 and undated (Box C1)
      - General, 1975 and undated, 2 folders (Box C1)
      - Circle of support, 1975-1976 and undated (Box C1)
      - Prison, 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box C1)
      - Post-prison, 1974-1981 (Box C1)
    - de Beauvoir, Simone, 1980-1984 (Box C2)
    - Bingham, Sallie, 1988-1993 (Box C2)
    - Crazies
      - 1977-1984 (Box C2)
      - Ward, John, 1979 and undated (Box C2)
    - Fieve, Ron, 1959-1962 and undated (Box C2)
    - Lawrence, JoAnn, 1991-1993 and undated (Box C2)
    - Millett, Kate, 1978-1992 and undated (Box C2)
    - Mother, 1958-1992 and undated (Box C2)
    - Poulin, Al, 1980-1981 (Box C2)
    - Putt, S. G., 1960-1987 (Box C2)
    - Rich, Adrienne, 1972-1997 and undated (Box C2)
    - Rivero, Isel
      - 1981-1991, undated; 1-3 of 13 folders (Box C2)
    - Rivero, Isel (Box C3)
      - 1981-1991, undated; 4-10 of 13 folders (Box C3)
    - Rivero, Isel (Box C4)
      - 1981-1991, undated; 11-13 of 13 folders (Box C4)
      - In Rwanda, 1994-1995 and undated (Box C4)
      - Poems, 1968-1987 and undated, 2 folders (Box C4)
    - Rorem, Ned, 1966-1997 and undated (Box C4)
    - Aunt Sallie and Aunt Sophie, 1964-1965 and undated (Box C4)
    - South Africa
      - Idasa, 1998 (Box C4)
      - 1998-1999 (Box C4)
    - Steinem, Gloria, 1989-1994 and undated (Box C4)
    - University of Denver, 1991-1997 and undated (Box C4)
    - Urban, Vladimir, 1980-1981 and undated (Box C4)
    - Yaddo, 1980 (Box C5)
  - Correspondence by Decade Subseries, 1950s-1990s and undated
    - 1950s (Box C5)
    - 1950s-1960s:Renoir, Schick, Crosby, Nehru (Box C5)
    - 1960s:
      - Gerhardi, William (Box C5)
      - Hai, Pho Ba (Box C5)
      - Nelson, Ralph (Box C5)
      - Stamper, Judy (Box C5)
      - Sorted by decade (Box C5)
      - de Vore, Paul (Box C5)
    - 1970s, 2 folders (Box C5)
    - 1970s-1980s:A-K, 9 folders (Box C5)
    - 1970s-1980s:L-W, 12 folders (Box C6)
    - 1980s, 1-3 of 5 folders (Box C6)
    - 1980s, 4-5 of 5 folders (Box C7)
    - 1990-1991: Ms. correspondence, 2 folders (Box C7)
    - 1991-1992: General, 3 folders (Box C7)
    - 1992: Ms. Correspondence, 2 folders (Box C8)
    - 1992-1993: General, 3 folders (Box C8)
    - 1993: Ms. Correspondence, 1-3 of 4 folders (Box C8)
    - 1993: Ms. Correspondence, 4 of 4 folders (Box C9)
    - 1993:New Zealand Faxes (Box C9)
    - 1994-1998: General, 1-6 of 7 folders (Box C9)
    - 1994-1998: General, 7 of 7 folders (Box C10)
    - 1990s, 3 folders (Box C10)
- Writings Series, 1940s-2002 and undated
  Largest in the collection, the Writings Series contains drafts, notes, manuscripts, reviews, and correspondence (both with editors and readers), as well as other material such as contracts and copyright agreements related to Morgan's novels, anthologies, and poetry. Individual subseries, arranged alphabetically, contain material relating to almost all of Morgan's book-length published works. Within each subseries, documents are in the original order to reflect the publishing process. Materials in the Poems, Other Writings by Morgan, Writings by Others, and Grants subseries are all in chronological order.
  The material related to the production of the Sisterhood is Global anthology is particularly extensive. It includes files on individual contributors, which contain ephemeral publications and correspondence providing insights into the lives of women in different parts of the world. Less extensive material on shorter published and unpublished works can be found in the Poems Subseries and Other Writings by Morgan Subseries. Particularly noteworthy in the latter are samples of Morgan's earliest writings, which reveal an acute sense of humour and sensitivity at an early age, and the many folders of Morgan's comments on other women's works. Finally, at the end of the Writings Series, there are a few manuscripts by other authors, including poetry and a dissertation about Morgan's work.
  - The Demon Lover Subseries, 1987-1999 and undated
    - Contracts and correspondence, 1987 and undated (Box W1)
    - Foreign rights and sub rights, 1988-1999, 3 folders (Box W1)
    - Production, 1988-1989 and undated (Box W1)
    - Mail on Demon Lover, 1989-1993 (Box W1)
  - Depth Perception Subseries, 1971-1993 and undated
    - Copyright file, 1971, 1978, 1980, 1981 (Box W1)
    - Permissions and sub rights, 1981, 1982, 1984 (Box W1)
    - Production, 1989-1993 (Box W1)
    - Reviews, 1981, 1983 and undated (Box W1)
  - Dry Your Smile Subseries, 1977-1988 and undated
    - Book layout, undated (Box W1)
    - Layout
      - Julian, undated (Box W1)
    - Layout
      - Chapter 1: Julian, undated (Box W1)
      - Chapter 2: Hope, undated (Box W1)
      - Chapter 3: Laurence, undated (Box W1)
      - Chapter 4: Laurence [3rd p. int.], undated (Box W1)
      - Blowout, undated (Box W1)
      - Chapter 6: Julian [1st p. Ahena], undated (Box W1)
      - Chapter 7: Laurence [1st p.], undated (Box W1)
      - Chapter 8: Julian [1st p. David], undated (Box W1)
      - Chapter 9: Iliana [3rd p. intern], undated (Box W1)
      - Chapter 10, undated (Box W1)
      - Chapter 11: Julian [1st p. "blur"], undated (Box W1)
      - Chapter 12: Julian [1st p. batter], undated (Box W1)
      - Chapter 13: Trio/Vigil J, L, I, undated (Box W1)
      - Chapter 14: Hope [1st p. death], undated (Box W1)
      - Chapter 15: Iliana [1st p.], undated (Box W1)
      - Epilogue, undated (Box W1)
    - Correspondence, 1977-1986 (Box W2)
    - Legal correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box W2)
    - Foreign correspondence, 1987-1988 and undated (Box W2)
    - Notes and critiques, 1986 and undated (Box W2)
    - Production, 1986-1987 and undated (Box W2)
  - Going Too Far Subseries, 1971-1981 and undated
    - French edition, 1977, 1978 (Box W2)
    - German edition, 1977-1981 (Box W2)
    - Legal, 1971-1977 (Box W2)
    - Permissions (to reprint), 1978-1980 (Box W2)
    - Reactions, 1977-1981, 3 folders (Box W2)
    - Reviews and ads, 1977 (Box W2)
    - Subsidiary, 1976-1977 and undated (Box W2)
  - A Hot January Subseries, 1997-1999 and undated
    - Pre-publication publication in magazines, 1997-1999, 2 folders (Box W3)
    - 1st pass, 1999 (Box W3)
    - 2nd pass, 1999 (Box W3)
    - Revisions, 1998-1999 (Box W3)
    - Production, 1998-1999, 2 folders (Box W3)
    - Old versions, undated, 2 folders (Box W3)
  - Lady of the Beasts Subseries, 1975-1980 and undated
    - Revisions, slides and illustrations (color), 1975, 1980 and undated (Box W3)
    - Revisions and comments, 1975-1976 and undated (Box W3)
    - Selected pieces published elsewhere, 1975, 1976 and undated (Box W3)
    - Copyright production, 1975-1976 and undated (Box W4)
    - Reactions, 1976-1978 and undated (Box W4)
    - Reviews and adverts, 1976-1978 and undated, 3 folders (Box W4)
    - Contracts and royalty statements, 1976-1980 (Box W4)
    - Background material, undated (Box W4)
  - Saturday's Child Subseries, 1999-2001 and undated
    - Manuscript, 1999, 1-4 of 5 folders (Box W4)
    - Manuscript, 1999, 5 of 5 folders (Box W5)
    - Manuscript, undated, 4 folders (Box W5)
    - Photocopies of black and white photos, undated (Box W5)
    - 1st proofs, 2000, 1-2 of 3 folders (Box W5)
    - 1st proofs, 2000, 3 of 3 folders (Box W6)
    - 2nd proofs, 2000, 3 folders (Box W6)
    - Proofs, 2000, 3 folders (Box W6)
    - 3rd proofs, 2000, 1 of 3 folders (Box W6)
    - 3rd proofs, 2000, 2-3 of 3 folders (Box W7)
    - Index, 2000 (Box W7)
    - Production material, 2000, 2001, 2 folders (Box W7)
  - Sisterhood is Forever Subseries, 2002 and undated
    - Manuscript, undated, 1-4 of 6 folders (Box W7)
    - Manuscript, undated, 5-6 of 6 folders (Box W8)
    - Final manuscript, undated, 6 folders (Box W8)
    - 1st pass, 2002, 1-2 of 5 folders (Box W8)
    - 1st pass, 2002, 3-5 of 5 folders (Box W9)
  - Sisterhood is Global Subseries, 1978-1997 and undated
    - Countries not included in the anthology, 1980-1982 and undated (Box W9)
    - Correspondence, book contracts, serial rights, 1980-1995 and undated, 4 folders (Box W9)
    - Doubleday meeting, 1984 and undated (Box W9)
    - Personal notes, drafts, undated (Box W9)
    - Meeting agendas, 1982-1983 and undated (Box W9)
    - 8-month budget, 1982-1983 (Box W9)
    - Foreign rights, 1983-1989 (Box W10)
    - Translators, 1982, 1984 and undated (Box W10)
    - Processor file, 1983 and undated (Box W10)
    - Contributors' payments, 1984-1985 and undated (Box W10)
    - Resource people, 1979-1982 and undated, 2 folders (Box W10)
    - Contributors
      - Afkhami, Mahnaz (Iran), 1981-1982 (Box W10)
      - Agosin, Marjorie (Chile), 1982-1984 (Box W10)
      - Aidoo, Ama Ata (Ghana), 1981-1985 (Box W10)
      - Al Falah, Noura (Kuwait), 1981-1984 and undated (Box W10)
      - Allaghi, Farida (Libya), 1980-1985 and undated (Box W10)
    - Contributors (Box W11)
      - Almana, Aisha (Saudi Arabia), 1981-1984 and undated (Box W11)
      - Aloni, Shulamit F. (Israel), 1978, 1981-1984 and undated (Box W11)
      - "Ames" (El Salvador), 1982 and undated (Box W11)
      - Antrobus, Peggy (Jamaica), 1981-1985 (Box W11)
      - Arungu-Olende, Mrs. and Rose Adhiambo (Kenya), 1983 and undated (Box W11)
      - As, Berit (Norway), 1981-1985 and undated, 2 folders (Box W11)
      - Badri, Anna (Sudan), 1981-1985 (Box W11)
      - Borja, Carola (Ecuador), 1982-1983 and undated (Box W11)
      - Calvera, Leonor (Argentina), 1983-1984 and undated (Box W11)
      - Chabaku, Motlalelupa (S. Africa), 1979-1985, 2 folders (Box W11)
      - Chiriac, Elena (Romania), 1982-1985 and undated (Box W11)
    - Contributors (Box W12)
      - Cuales, Sonia (Dutch-Caribbean), 1982-1984 and undated (Box W12)
      - de Beauvoir, Simone (France), 1981-1985 and undated, 2 folders (Box W12)
      - thi Dinh, Nguyen (Vietnam), 1981-1984 and undated (Box W12)
      - Dowse, Sarah and Giles, Pat (Australia), 1981-1982, 1984 and undated (Box W12)
      - Falcon, Lidia (Spain), 1981-1985 and undated, 2 folders (Box W12)
      - Ghurayybi, Rose (Lebanon), 1981-1984 and undated (Box W12)